Mackenzie Urquhart-Cronish

September 2009 - June 2013

Botany Dept. & Biodiversity Research Centre University of British Columbia mackenzie.urq@gmail.com macurqcron.github.io

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My PhD research explores the demography of range expansion and its genetic consequences for range edge populations. My work advances our conceptual understanding of the factors affecting species ranges by developing new theoretical models and conducting empirical studies with plants (i.e., fieldwork, greenhouse experiments, evolutionary genomics) in nature along contrasting spatiotemporal scales (e.g., latitude vs. elevation) to test and refine existing range expansion theory. Specifically, my work aims to identify when and where we expect range expansion to influence spatial variation in genetic load and/or mating-system traits and how these feedback to affect the long-term persistence of edge populations in nature.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. September 2018 - August 2024

University of British Columbia Supervisor: Amy Angert

Department of Botany

M.Sc. September 2014 - July 2016

University of Toronto Supervisor: Marla Sokolowski

Department of Ecology & Evolutionary Biology

B.Sc. Hon. with distinction

University of Toronto Supervisor: Marla Sokolowski

Double major: Ecology & Evolutionary Biology and Animal Physiology

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-reviewed

- 5. **M.** Urquhart-Cronish, A.L. Angert, S. P. Otto, and A. MacPherson (2024). Density-dependent selection during range expansion affects expansion load in life-history traits. *The American Naturalist*. 203(3), 382-392. https://doi.org/10.1086/728599
- 4. R. Germain, M. Urquhart-Cronish, N. Jones, M. Mayfield, and M. Raymundo (2022). The strength and direction of (mal)adaptation depends on neighbour density and the environment. *Journal of Ecology* 110(3), 514-525. https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.13838
- 3. K.A. Thompson, M. Urquhart-Cronish, K.D. Whitney, L.H. Rieseberg, and D. Schluter (2021). Patterns, predictors, and consequences of dominance in hybrids. *The American Naturalist*. 197(3), E72-E88. https://doi.org/10.1086/712603 (*Honorable mention: Best student paper award 2022*)
- 2. M. Urquhart-Cronish, and S. P. Otto (2019). Gender and language use in scientific grant writing. FACETS. 4: 442-458. https://doi.org/10.1139/facets-2018-0039 press: University Affairs article
- 1. M. Urquhart-Cronish and M. B. Sokolowski (2014). Gene-environment interplay in *Drosophila melanogaster*: chronic nutritional deprivation in larval life affects adult fecal output. *Journal of Insect Physiology.* 69: 95-100. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jinsphys.2014.06.001

AWARDS

Scholarships, fellowships, & awards

2024	SSE W.D. Hamilton Award winner	\$500 USD
2024	SSE W.D. Hamilton Award finalist	\$500 USD
2022	Kit Malkin Scholarship	\$775 CAD
2020 – 2021	NSERC CGS D	$$35\ 000\ \mathrm{CAD}$
2020	L'Oréal - France-Canada Research Fund Fellowship	$$5~000~\mathrm{CAD}$
2019	Vladimir J. Krajina Prize in Plant Ecology	\$1 200 CAD
2019	Samantha Hicks Memorial Prize	1050 CAD
2018 – 2020	NSERC PGS D	\$42 000 CAD
2018-2022	UBC Four-Year Doctoral Fellowship $(\frac{3}{4} \text{ declined})$	\$72 800 CAD
2015 & 2016	Frederick P. Ide Graduate Award	2020 CAD
2015 – 2016	NSERC CGS M	\$17 500 CAD
2014	EEB Entrance Scholarship	\$1 000 CAD
2012	Victoria College In-Course Regents Scholarship	\$1 000 CAD

Research grants

2022	Botanical Society of America Graduate Student Research Award	\$1 500 USD
2022	The American Society of Naturalists Student Research Award	2000 USD
2021	Lewis and Clark Fund for Exploration and Field Research	$$5~000~\mathrm{USD}$
2020	RC Lewontin Award—Society for the Study of Evolution	\$2 500 USD

Travel awards

2023	Graduate Student Travel Award (UBC)	\$500 CAD
2016	School of Graduate Studies Conference Grant	\$500 CAD
2016	Harold H. Harvey Travel Award	\$400 CAD
2014	Imperial College Travel Grant	$£500~\mathrm{UK}$

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Mentorship

2023	Lauren McBurnie	Directed Studies (UBC)
2019 – 2020	Olivia Rahn	UBC 'SURE' Award, Directed Studies, & NSERC USRA (UBC)

Courses taught

2024	Teaching assistant	Fundamentals of Ecology (UBC)
2023	Teaching assistant	Evolutionary Ecology (UBC)
2022, 2023	Teaching assistant	Integrative Science Research Development Project (UBC)
2021, 2022	Teaching assistant	Fundamentals of Biostatistics (UBC)
2020, 2021, 202	2 Teaching assistant	Plant Ecology (UBC)
2020	Teaching assistant	Plants and People (UBC)
2015, 2016	Teaching assistant	From Genomes to Ecosystems (U of T)
2014	Teaching assistant	Adaptation and Biodiversity (U of T)

PRESENTATIONS

Invited

2024	Third SSE & ESEB Joint Congress	Montreal, QC, Canada (upcoming)
	Symposium: Ecology and the Evolution of Reproductive Traits	
2024	Third SSE & ESEB Joint Congress	Online
	W.D. Hamilton Award Symposium	

Contributed

[‡] Talk [†] Poster *Presentation award				
2024	Canadian Society for Ecology & Evolution [‡]	Vancouver, BC, Canada		
2023	Ecology & Evolution Retreat ^{‡*}	Brackendale, BC, Canada		
2023	Evolution Meeting [‡]	Albuquerque, NM, USA		
2022	Botany Graduate Student Symposium [‡]	Vancouver, BC, Canada		
2021	Ecology & Evolution Virtual Retreat [‡]	Online		
2019	Ecology & Evolution Retreat [†]	Brackendale, BC, Canada		
2018	Ecology & Evolution Retreat [†]	Brackendale, BC, Canada		
2016	Canadian Society for Ecology & Evolution [‡]	St. John's, NL, Canada		
2016	Ontario Ecology, Ethology & Evolution Colloquium [‡]	Toronto, ON, Canada		
2013	Ontario Ecology, Ethology & Evolution Colloquium [†]	London, ON, Canada		
2013	U of T EEB Department Undergraduate Poster Fair $^{\dagger *}$	Toronto, ON, Canada		

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Technical experience

2022, 2023	Visiting Genomics Researcher with Dr. Lila Fishman	Missoula, MT, USA
2018	Field Crew Leader with Dr. Amy Angert	Vancouver, BC, Canada
2018	CIEE Website Developer with Dr. Diane Srivastava	Vancouver, BC, Canada
2017	Field and Greenhouse Technician with Dr. Rachel Germain	Vancouver, BC, Canada
2017	Grant Writer/Research Assistant with Dr. Sarah P. Otto	Vancouver, BC, Canada
2016-2017	Data Analyst with Dr. Jeannette Whitton	Vancouver, BC, Canada
2013-2014	Research Assistant with Dr. Marla B. Sokolowski	Toronto, ON, Canada
2012	Research Assistant with Dr. Don Jackson	Toronto, ON, Canada

COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT & SERVICE

Positions held

2022 – 2023	BRC Post-Doc Search Committee	UBC Biodiversity Research Centre
2021-	UBC Graduate Representative	Canadian Society for Ecology & Evolution
2018-	Webmaster	Angert Lab (UBC)
2020 – 2021	President	UBC Botany Graduate Students' Association
2020 – 2021	Office Space Use Committee	UBC Biodiversity Research Centre
2019	Co-director "Huts" Skit	UBC Botany & Zoology Departments
2019 – 2020	Wilderness First Aid Coordinator	UBC Botany & Zoology Departments
2017 – 2018	"Coexisting with Coyotes" Data Analyst	Stanley Park Ecology Society
2016 – 2017	Museum Outreach Education Volunteer	Beaty Biodiversity Museum
2016	Volunteer Tutor	U of T Saturday Program
2015 – 2016	Lead Plenary Coordinator	Ontario Ecology, Ethology & Evolution Colloquium

Reviewer history

$A cademic\ journals$

2024 Journal	of	Evolutionary	Biology
--------------	----	--------------	---------

2022 Oikos, Journal of Heredity

 $2021 \quad Journal\ of\ Biogeography,\ Proc.\ Royal\ Soc.\ B.$

2020 FACETS